Preliminary Guide to the University Marshal Records, 1942-1989 UA.01.09.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
University Marshal records
1942-1989
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. University Marshal
UA.01.09.0001
40 Linear Feet
The Office of the University Marshal is responsible for some of Duke University's most significant occasions: opening convocation, Founders' Day, and commencement. The University Marshal Records include correspondence, lists of candidates for degrees, memos, programs, financial records, records of the awarding of honorary degrees, minutes of the commencement committee, statistics, speeches, and other printed materials. Major subjects include information and procedures related to Founder's Day, baccalaureate services, convocations, and commencements; and files that detail the daily operation of the Office of the University Marshal. English.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The University Marshal Records was received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1967 (A67-87), 1968 (A68-346), 1975 (A75-102), 1979 (A79-91), 1982 (A82-75), 1988 (A88-0025), 1993 (A93-82), and 2014 (UA2014.0081).
Historical Note
The Office of the University Marshal is responsible for organizing details and making decisions about the operation of some of Duke University's most significant occasions: opening convocation, Founders' Day, and commencement. The University Marshal holds both administrative and ceremonial responsibilities. The office's most public responsibility is to carry the University Mace and lead the procession at graduation. To many, the University Marshal's position is the embodiment of university traditions.
Collection Overview
The University Marshal Records includes correspondence, lists of candidates for degrees, memos, programs, financial records, records of the awarding of honorary degrees, minutes of the commencement committee, statistics, speeches, and other printed materials. Major subjects include information and procedures related to Founder's Day, baccalaureate services, convocations, and commencements; and files that detail the daily operation of the Office of the University Marshal.
The University Marshall Records is arranged by accession date. These accessions are given in chronological order. The descriptions given for each box are general descriptions of the contents of the box and are not folder titles. There is some consistency in the contents of the boxes from one accession to another, but the folder titles are not identical.
Access to all folders in Box 3 is RESTRICTED. Please consult University Archives staff.
Related Material
Office of Special Events and University Ceremonies Records, UA.01.04.0001, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Commencement Exercises Reference Collection, 01.11.0041, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Douglas M. Knight Records, 03.59.0001, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Universities and colleges -- Administration; Baccalaureate addresses -- Duke University; Duke University. University Marshal; Duke University. University Marshal; Duke University; Duke University -- Administration; Duke University -- History -- 20th century
- 1967 and 1968 Additions (Accession A67-087 and Accession 68-345), 1940-1970
  Access Restrictions
  Access to all folders in Box 3 is RESTRICTED. Please consult University Archives staff.
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes information about convocation, commencement, Founder's Day, baccalaureate services, honorary degrees, and the daily business of the Office of the University Marshal. The Office files include correspondence, memos, statistics, receipts, lists of dissertation titles, memos on ceremonial procedures, lists of degree candidates, information about diplomas, and information on honors and prizes.
  - Contents of Box 1, 1940-1950 (Box 1)
    - Lists of Candidates (Box 1)
    - Baccalaureate Services (Box 1)
    - Commencement Procedures (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Commencement Reception (Box 1)
    - Requisitions (Box 1)
    - Statistics (Box 1)
    - Diplomas (Box 1)
    - Form Letters (Box 1)
    - Founder's Day (Box 1)
    - Honorary Degrees (Box 1)
    - Marshals (Box 1)
    - Honors and Prizes (Box 1)
    - Memos (Box 1)
    - Procedures (Box 1)
    - Programs (Box 1)
  - Contents of Box 2, 1960-1970 (Box 2)
    - Commencement (Box 2)
    - Form Letters (Box 2)
    - Diplomas (Box 2)
    - Finances (Box 2)
    - Procedures (Box 2)
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Statistics (Box 2)
    - Honorary Degrees (Box 2)
    - Speakers (Box 2)
    - Marshals (Box 2)
    - Honors and Prizes (Box 2)
    - Convocations (Box 2)
    - Baccalaureate (Box 2)
    - Honorary Degrees (Box 2)
    - Founder's Day (Box 2)
  - Contents of Box 3, 1953-1967 (Box 3)
    Contains correspondence, nominations, committee meeting minutes, memos, and recommendations about the awarding of honorary degrees.
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Access to all folders in Box 3 is RESTRICTED: Personal Privacy.
- 1975 Addition (Accession A75-102), 1969-1976
  Includes information about convocation, commencement, Founder's Day, baccalaureate services, honorary degrees, and the daily business of the Office of the University Marshal. The Office files include correspondence, statistics, receipts, lists of dissertation titles, memos on ceremonial procedures, lists of degree candidates, information about diplomas, and information on honors and prizes.
  - Contents of Box 4, 1969-1974 (Box 4)
    - Lists of Candidates for Degrees (Box 4)
    - Convocation (Box 4)
    - Commencement (Box 4)
    - Baccalaureate (Box 4)
    - Founder's Day (Box 4)
    - Finances (Box 4)
    - Form Letters (Box 4)
    - Statistics (Box 4)
    - Correspondence (Box 4)
    - Honorary Degrees (Box 4)
    - Invitations (Box 4)
    - Diplomas (Box 4)
    - Marshals (Box 4)
    - Speakers (Box 4)
    - Security (Box 4)
  - Contents of Box 5, 1973-1976 (Box 5)
    - Marshals (Box 5)
    - Publicity (Box 5)
    - Printing (Box 5)
    - Procedures (Box 5)
    - Programs (Box 5)
    - Speakers (Box 5)
    - Josten's (Box 5)
    - Statistics (Box 5)
    - Accounting and Budgeting (Box 5)
    - Baccalaureate (Box 5)
    - Calendar (Box 5)
    - Commencement (Box 5)
    - Correspondence (Box 5)
    - Forms (Box 5)
    - Founder's Day (Box 5)
    - Honorary Degrees (Box 5)
    - Josten's (Box 5)
- 1979 Additions (Accession A79-091), 1974-1978
  - Contents of Box 6, 1974-1976 (Box 6)
    - Commencement (Box 6)
    - Correspondence (Box 6)
    - Diplomas (Box 6)
    - Founder's Day (Box 6)
    - Honorary Degrees (Box 6)
    - Accounting and Budgeting (Box 6)
    - Josten's (Box 6)
    - Procedures (Box 6)
    - Operating Expenses (Box 6)
    - Marshals (Box 6)
    - President's Luncheon (Box 6)
    - Statistics (Box 6)
    - Academic Council (Box 6)
    - Baccalaureate (Box 6)
    - Clothing (Box 6)
  - Contents of Box 7, 1967-1978 (Box 7)
    - Commencement (Box 7)
    - Programs (Box 7)
    - Operating Expenses (Box 7)
    - President Sanford (Box 7)
    - Officers (Box 7)
    - Speakers (Box 7)
    - Statistics (Box 7)
    - Apparel (Box 7)
    - Calendar (Box 7)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 7)
    - Choir (Box 7)
    - Lists of Candidates (Box 7)
    - Procedures (Box 7)
    - Honorary Degrees (Box 7)
    - Academic Honors (Box 7)
    - Marshals (Box 7)
    - Josten's (Box 7)
    - Prizes and Awards (Box 7)
- 1982 Addition (Accession A82-75), 1978-1980 and 1984
  - Contents of Box 8, 1978-1980 (Box 8)
    - Accounting and Budgeting (Box 8)
    - Professional Services (Box 8)
    - Diplomas (Box 8)
    - Baccalaureate (Box 8)
    - Addresses (Box 8)
    - Correspondence (Box 8)
    - Procedures (Box 8)
    - Publicity (Box 8)
    - Academic Honors (Box 8)
    - Josten's (Box 8)
    - President's Luncheon (Box 8)
    - Statistics (Box 8)
  - Contents of Box 9, 1978-1980, 1984 (Box 9)
    - Teacher Certification (Box 9)
    - Commencement Committee (Box 9)
    - Correspondence (Box 9)
    - Diplomas (Box 9)
    - Founder's Day (Box 9)
    - Procedures (Box 9)
    - Honorary Degrees (Box 9)
    - Awards and Prizes (Box 9)
    - Calendars (Box 9)
    - Speeches (Box 9)
    - Statistics (Box 9)
    - Marshals (Box 9)
    - Student Speeches, Tryouts, 1984 (Box 9)
    - Josten's (Box 9)
- 1988 Addition (Accession A88-025), 1980-1985
  Includes information about convocation, commencement, Founder's Day, baccalaureate services, honorary degrees, and the daily business of the Office of the University Marshal. This series also includes information about the Fuqua School of Business Dedication and the Robert H. James Dedication. The Office files include correspondence, statistics, receipts, lists of dissertation titles, memos on ceremonial procedures, lists of degree candidates, information about diplomas, and information on honors and prizes.
  - Contents of Box 10, 1980-1982 (Box 10)
    - Awards and Prizes (Box 10)
    - Josten's (Box 10)
    - Marshals (Box 10)
    - Bryan Center Opening (Box 10)
    - Senior Day (Box 10)
    - Commencement (Box 10)
    - Procedures (Box 10)
    - Baccalaureate (Box 10)
    - Speakers (Box 10)
    - Programs (Box 10)
    - Graduation Weekend (Box 10)
    - Correspondence (Box 10)
    - Statistics (Box 10)
    - Academic Apparel (Box 10)
    - Accounting and Budgeting (Box 10)
    - Lists of Candidates (Box 10)
  - Contents of Box 11, 1980-1981 (Box 11)
    - Dissertation Titles (Box 11)
    - Correspondence (Box 11)
    - Commencement (Box 11)
    - Diplomas (Box 11)
    - Honorary Degrees (Box 11)
    - Founder's Day (Box 11)
    - Academic Honors (Box 11)
    - Josten's (Box 11)
    - President's Luncheon (Box 11)
    - Calendar of Events (Box 11)
    - Baccalaureate Program (Box 11)
    - Speeches (Box 11)
    - Statistics (Box 11)
  - Contents of Box 12, 1981-1982 (Box 12)
    - Accounting and Budgeting (Box 12)
    - Lists of Degree Candidates (Box 12)
    - Dissertation Titles (Box 12)
    - Commencement (Box 12)
    - Correspondence (Box 12)
    - Diplomas (Box 12)
    - Bulletins (Box 12)
    - Honorary Degrees (Box 12)
    - Procedures (Box 12)
    - Academic Honors (Box 12)
  - Contents of Box 13, 1982-1983 (Box 13)
    - Accounting and Budgeting (Box 13)
    - Lists of Degree Candidates (Box 13)
    - Dissertation Titles (Box 13)
    - Commencement (Box 13)
    - Correspondence (Box 13)
    - Diplomas (Box 13)
    - Bulletins (Box 13)
    - Honorary Degrees (Box 13)
    - Procedures (Box 13)
    - Academic Honors (Box 13)
    - Founder's Day (Box 13)
    - President's Luncheon (Box 13)
  - Contents of Box 14, 1982-1983, 1983-1984 (Box 14)
    - Marshals (Box 14)
    - Annual Faculty Meeting (Box 14)
    - Fuqua School of Business Dedication (Box 14)
    - Robert H. James Dedication (Box 14)
    - Opening Convocation (Box 14)
    - Procedures (Box 14)
    - Calendar of Events (Box 14)
    - Programs (Box 14)
    - Organ Recital (Box 14)
    - Reception (Box 14)
    - Commencement (Box 14)
    - Baccalaureate (Box 14)
    - Statistics (Box 14)
    - Correspondence (Box 14)
    - Accounting and Budgeting (Box 14)
    - Operating Expenses (Box 14)
    - Lists of Degree Candidates (Box 14)
    - Teaching Certification (Box 14)
    - Commencement Committee (Box 14)
  - Contents of Box 15, 1983-1984, 1984-1985 (Box 15)
    - Commencement Committee (Box 15)
    - Correspondence (Box 15)
    - Diplomas (Box 15)
    - Honorary Degrees (Box 15)
    - Founder's Day (Box 15)
    - Marshals (Box 15)
    - President's Luncheon (Box 15)
    - Josten's (Box 15)
    - Awards and Prizes (Box 15)
    - Academic Honors (Box 15)
    - Teer Dedication (Box 15)
    - Organ Recital (Box 15)
    - Calendar of Events (Box 15)
    - Procedures (Box 15)
    - Accounting and Budgeting (Box 15)
    - Operating Expenses (Box 15)
  - Contents of Box 16, 1984-1985 (Box 16)
    - Baccalaureate (Box 16)
    - Lists of Degree Candidates (Box 16)
    - Dissertation Titles (Box 16)
    - Commencement Committee (Box 16)
    - Correspondence (Box 16)
    - Diplomas (Box 16)
    - Founder's Day (Box 16)
    - Honorary Degrees (Box 16)
    - Academic Honors (Box 16)
    - Awards and Prizes (Box 16)
    - Marshals (Box 16)
    - Third World Symposium (Box 16)
    - Willimon Installation (Box 16)
    - Trinity College Gazebo (Box 16)
    - Calendar of Events (Box 16)
    - Statistics (Box 16)
    - Speakers (Box 16)
- 1993 Additions (Accession A93-82), 1985-1989
  - Contents of Box 17, 1985-1986 (Box 17)
    - Academic Records (Box 17)
    - Accounting (Box 17)
    - Baccalaureate (Box 17)
    - Correspondence (Box 17)
    - Dissertation Titles (Box 17)
    - Diploma Information (Box 17)
    - Founder's Day (Box 17)
    - Honorary Degree Candidates (Box 17)
    - Josten's (Box 17)
    - Academic Honors (Box 17)
    - Invitations (Box 17)
  - Contents of Box 18, 1985-1987 (Box 18)
    - Graduation Marshals (Box 18)
    - Procedures (Box 18)
    - Programs (Box 18)
    - Calendar of Events (Box 18)
    - Josten's (Box 18)
    - Statistics (Box 18)
    - Speeches (Box 18)
    - Correspondence (Box 18)
    - Suggestions (Box 18)
    - Accounting (Box 18)
    - Administrative and Operating Services (Box 18)
    - Lists of Candidates (Box 18)
    - Dissertation Titles (Box 18)
    - Teacher Certification (Box 18)
  - Contents of Box 19, 1986-1987 (Box 19)
    - Commencement Committee (Box 19)
    - Correspondence (Box 19)
    - Deaths (Box 19)
    - Diplomas (Box 19)
    - Honorary Degrees (Box 19)
    - Josten's (Box 19)
    - Founder's Day (Box 19)
    - Graduation Marshals (Box 19)
    - Calendar of Events (Box 19)
    - Graduation Programs (Box 19)
    - Reception (Box 19)
    - Commencement (Box 19)
    - Speeches (Box 19)
    - Statistics (Box 19)
  - Contents of Box 20, 1987-1988 (Box 20)
    - Dissertation Titles (Box 20)
    - Commencement Committee (Box 20)
    - Correspondence (Box 20)
    - Diplomas (Box 20)
    - Founder's Day (Box 20)
    - Honorary Degrees (Box 20)
    - Josten's (Box 20)
    - Academic Honors (Box 20)
    - Invitations (Box 20)
    - Marshals (Box 20)
    - Graduation Procedures (Box 20)
    - Statistics (Box 20)
    - Speeches (Box 20)
  - Contents of Box 21, 1988-1989 (Box 21)
    - Academic Honors (Box 21)
    - Invitations (Box 21)
    - Marshals (Box 21)
    - Convocation (Box 21)
    - Calendar of Events (Box 21)
    - Josten's (Box 21)
    - Programs (Box 21)
    - Publicity (Box 21)
    - Speeches and Sermons (Box 21)
    - Statistics (Box 21)
    - Accounting (Box 21)
    - Administrative and Operating Services (Box 21)
    - Baccalaureate (Box 21)
    - Degree Candidates (Box 21)
  - Contents of Box 22, 1988-1989 (Box 22)
    - Accounting (Box 22)
    - Operating Services (Box 22)
    - Baccalaureate Information (Box 22)
    - Degree Candidates (Box 22)
    - Correspondence (Box 22)
    - Dissertation Titles (Box 22)
    - Teacher Certification (Box 22)
    - Commencement Committee (Box 22)
    - Josten's (Box 22)
    - Diplomas (Box 22)
    - Founder's Day (Box 22)
    - Honorary Degrees (Box 22)
    - Academic Honors (Box 22)
- 2014 Addition (Accession UA2014.0081), 1988-2007
  Scope and Contents
  These files were generally arranged by academic year, with the same file titles used each year. As in previous accessions, these files contain lists of candidates, commencement procedures, founders day, statistics, dedications, memorials, programs, invitations, committee meeting minutes, academic honors, trustee information, and correspondence, among other materials. Along with the files arranged chronologically by academic year, there are several files on assorted topics related to the duties of the University Marshal that are not interfiled chronologically, as well as files on equipment rentals in 2006-20007 (the rest of the files from this academic year were not with this accession).
  This accession also includes materials related to the sesquicentennial celebrations in 1988 and 1999, as well as VHS video recordings of baccalaureate services and commencement exercises in 1997 and 2001, and audiocassette recordings of convocations, commencements, and baccalaureate services from 1990-2000.
  - Assorted files, 1989-2005 (Box 23)
  - Chronological files, 1998-1999 (Box 23)
  - Chronological files, 1998-1999 (Box 24)
  - Chronological files, 1999-2000 (Box 24)
  - Chronological files, 1999-2000 (Box 25)
  - Chronological files, 2000-2001 (Box 25)
  - Chronological files, 2000-2001 (Box 26)
  - Chronological files, 2000-2001 (Box 27)
  - Chronological files, 2001-2002 (Box 27)
  - Chronological files, 2001-2002 (Box 28)
  - Chronological files, 2002-2003 (Box 28)
  - Chronological files, 2002-2003 (Box 29)
  - Chronological files, 2002-2003 (Box 30)
  - Chronological files, 2003-2004 (Box 30)
  - Chronological files, 2003-2004 (Box 31)
  - Chronological files, 2003-2004 (Box 32)
  - Chronological files, 2005-2006 (Box 32)
  - Chronological files, 2005-2006 (Box 33)
  - Equipment rentals, 2006-2007 (Box 32)
  - Sesquicentennial files, 1988-1989 (Box 33)
  - Sesquicentennial files, 1988-1989 (Box 34)
  - VHS video recordings, 1997, 2001; 6 tapes VHS
  - Audiocassette recordings, 1990-2000; 47 audiocassettes